[
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "India's territorial limit extends towards the sea up to how many nautical miles from the coast?",
        "answer": "12 nautical miles",
        "choices": [
            "12 nautical miles",
            "200 nautical miles",
            "24 nautical miles",
            "100 nautical miles"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "India's Exclusive Economic Zone extends towards the sea up to how many nautical miles from the coast?",
        "answer": "200 nautical miles",
        "choices": [
            "200 nautical miles",
            "12 nautical miles",
            "24 nautical miles",
            "100 nautical miles"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "How many latitudes are there on the globe drawn at 1 degree interval?",
        "answer": 179,
        "choices": [
            179,
            180,
            360,
            359
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "How much is the difference between Indian Standard Time (IST) and Greenwich Mean Time (GMT)?",
        "answer": "plus 5 hour 30 minutes",
        "choices": [
            "plus 5 hour 30 minutes",
            "minus 5 hour 30 minutes",
            "minus 4 hour 30 minutes",
            "plus 4 hour 30 minutes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "On which plateau, the Tropic of Cancer and the Indian Standard Time intersect each other?",
        "answer": "Baghelkhand",
        "choices": [
            "Baghelkhand",
            "Bundelkhand",
            "Kaimur",
            "Chhota-Nagpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "On which longitude does Indian Standard Time coicide?",
        "answer": "82deg 30min E",
        "choices": [
            "82deg 30min E",
            "85deg 30min W",
            "88deg 30min E",
            "80deg 30min W"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Difference of one degree longitude will correspond to how much time",
        "answer": "4 minutes",
        "choices": [
            "4 minutes",
            "6 minutes",
            "60 minutes",
            "30 minutes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "What is the local time of Thimphu (Bhutan) located at 90deg E longitude when the time at Greenwich (0deg) is 12:00 noon?",
        "answer": "6:00 pm",
        "choices": [
            "6:00 pm",
            "4:00 pm",
            "5:00 pm",
            "6:00 am"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The foothills region of Himalayas is",
        "answer": "Shiwalik",
        "choices": [
            "Shiwalik",
            "Great Himalayas",
            "Trans-Himalayas",
            "Lesser Himalayas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which of the following areas is not landslide-prone area?",
        "answer": "Eastern Ghats",
        "choices": [
            "Eastern Ghats",
            "Western Ghats",
            "Himalayan Region",
            "North-Eastern Region"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The highest peak in the Eastern Ghats of India is",
        "answer": "Arma Konda (Jhindhagada)",
        "choices": [
            "Arma Konda (Jhindhagada)",
            "Mahendragiri",
            "Anai Mudi",
            "Kanchenjunga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The highest peak in the Western Ghats of India is",
        "answer": "Anai Mudi",
        "choices": [
            "Anai Mudi",
            "Mahendragiri",
            "Arma Konda (Jhindhagada)",
            "Kanchenjunga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The highest mountain peak in India?",
        "answer": "K2 (Godwin-Austen)",
        "choices": [
            "K2 (Godwin-Austen)",
            "Everest",
            "Nanda Devi",
            "Kanchenjunga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The Kailash Range is part of which larger mountain system?",
        "answer": "Trans-Himalaya",
        "choices": [
            "Trans-Himalaya",
            "Great Himalayas",
            "Shiwalik",
            "Lesser Himalayas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Mount Everest lies in which mountain range?",
        "answer": "Great Himalayas",
        "choices": [
            "Great Himalayas",
            "Trans-Himalaya",
            "Shiwalik",
            "Lesser Himalayas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which is the highest mountain peak entirely within India (not on the border)?",
        "answer": "Nanda Devi",
        "choices": [
            "Nanda Devi",
            "Kanchenjunga",
            "Trishul",
            "Kamet"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Shiwalik series was formed in",
        "answer": "Cenozoic",
        "choices": [
            "Cenozoic",
            "Proterozoic",
            "Mesozoic",
            "Palaeozoic"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Someshwar range is a part of which of the following mountain ranges?",
        "answer": "Shiwalik",
        "choices": [
            "Shiwalik",
            "Satpura",
            "Vindhayan",
            "Eastern Ghats"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Atal Tunnel is across which one of the following Himalayan ranges?",
        "answer": "Eastern Pir Panjal",
        "choices": [
            "Eastern Pir Panjal",
            "Western Pir Panjal",
            "Zanskar",
            "Ladakh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "At which of the following hills the Eastern Ghats join the Western Ghats?",
        "answer": "Nilgiri Hills",
        "choices": [
            "Nilgiri Hills",
            "Palni Hills",
            "Anaimudi Hills",
            "Shevaroy Hills"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Western Ghats in Maharashtra and Karnataka is known as",
        "answer": "Sahyadri",
        "choices": [
            "Sahyadri",
            "Nilgiri",
            "Shiwalik",
            "Nandi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The Hills situated closer to Kanyakumari are",
        "answer": "Cardamom Hills",
        "choices": [
            "Cardamom Hills",
            "Nilgiri Hills",
            "Anaialai Hills",
            "Shevaroy Hills"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which of the following is not a part of the Meghalaya Plateau?",
        "answer": "Bhuban Hills",
        "choices": [
            "Bhuban Hills",
            "Garo Hills",
            "Khasi Hills",
            "Jaintia Hills"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Extra peninsular mountains of India were formed during",
        "answer": "Cenozoic Era",
        "choices": [
            "Cenozoic Era",
            "Palaeozoic Era",
            "Aozoic Era",
            "Mesozoic Era"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Chhota-Nagpur Plateau is a",
        "answer": "front sloping",
        "choices": [
            "front sloping",
            "pitfall",
            "foothill",
            "plain subland"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which one of the following districts does not have Dharwar geological formations?",
        "answer": "Rohtas",
        "choices": [
            "Rohtas",
            "Jamui",
            "Munger",
            "Nawada"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "How many coastal states are there in India?",
        "answer": "Nine",
        "choices": [
            "Nine",
            "Eight",
            "Thirteen",
            "Eleven"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Island group Lakshadweep is",
        "answer": "Accumulation of Coral Reef",
        "choices": [
            "Accumulation of Coral Reef",
            "Accumulation of Volcanic substances",
            "Sedimentated Soil",
            "None of these"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Lakshadweep consists of how many islands?",
        "answer": 36,
        "choices": [
            36,
            16,
            17,
            26
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The Ramsar Convention is associated with the conservation of",
        "answer": "Wetlands",
        "choices": [
            "Wetlands",
            "Drylands",
            "Forests",
            "Hills"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which gas contributes to global warming through its greenhouse effect?",
        "answer": "All of these",
        "choices": [
            "All of these",
            "Methane",
            "Nitrous Oxide",
            "Carbon Dioxide"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which of the following gas is responsible for the depletion of Ozone layer?",
        "answer": "Chlorofluorocarbons",
        "choices": [
            "Chlorofluorocarbons",
            "Carbon Monoxide",
            "Carbon Dioxide",
            "Nitrous Oxide"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "What is the percentage of forest and tree cover in the total geographical area of India according to Indian State of Forest Report 2023?",
        "answer": "25.17 percent",
        "choices": [
            "25.17 percent",
            "21.76 percent",
            "3.41 percent",
            "91.33 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "What is the percentage of forest cover in the total geographical area of India according to Indian State of Forest Report 2023?",
        "answer": "21.76 percent",
        "choices": [
            "21.76 percent",
            "25.17 percent",
            "3.41 percent",
            "91.33 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The largest percentage of forest area is in",
        "answer": "Lakshadweep",
        "choices": [
            "Lakshadweep",
            "Mizoram",
            "Andman & Nicobar",
            "Madhya Pradesh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "State having largest forest cover in India",
        "answer": "Madhya Pradesh",
        "choices": [
            "Madhya Pradesh",
            "Arunanchal Pradesh",
            "Chhattisgarh",
            "Sikkim"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "In National Park protection is given to",
        "answer": "Whole Ecosystem",
        "choices": [
            "Whole Ecosystem",
            "Only Fauna",
            "Only Flora",
            "Only Birds"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which of the following areas in India does not grow tropical wet evergreen forests?",
        "answer": "Eastern Ghats",
        "choices": [
            "Eastern Ghats",
            "Western Ghats",
            "Andaman Islands",
            "North-Eastern Region"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "In which forest do the majority of species of birds inhabit the mountainous areas?",
        "answer": "Pine Forest",
        "choices": [
            "Pine Forest",
            "Bush Forest",
            "Oak Forest",
            "Maple Forest"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "India's first Dolphin Observatory is being built in",
        "answer": "Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar",
            "Kolkata",
            "Odisha",
            "Delhi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The state of India with maximum number of wildlife sanctuaries is",
        "answer": "Maharashtra",
        "choices": [
            "Maharashtra",
            "Karnataka",
            "Madhya Pradesh",
            "Tamil Nadu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which one of the following is the well-publicised wildife campaign in the world launched in 1973?",
        "answer": "Project Tiger",
        "choices": [
            "Project Tiger",
            "Sunderbans Project",
            "Project Big Cat",
            "Project Elephant"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which one of the following is not included under in-situ conservation?",
        "answer": "Botanical Garden",
        "choices": [
            "Botanical Garden",
            "National Parks",
            "Wildlife Sanctuaries",
            "Biosphere Reserves"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Total Ramsar sites in India?",
        "answer": 91,
        "choices": [
            91,
            90,
            19,
            45
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The Radcliffe Line demarcates the boundary between",
        "answer": "India-Pakistan",
        "choices": [
            "India-Pakistan",
            "India-Bangladesh",
            "India-Afghanistan",
            "India-China"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The McMahon Line, often in dispute, is related to the boundary between India and",
        "answer": "China",
        "choices": [
            "China",
            "Bangladesh",
            "Pakistan",
            "Myanmar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The Durand Line (1893) originally separated British India from",
        "answer": "Afghanistan",
        "choices": [
            "Afghanistan",
            "China",
            "Nepal",
            "Bhutan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The Treaty of Sugauli (1816) defined India’s border with which country?",
        "answer": "Nepal",
        "choices": [
            "Nepal",
            "Bhutan",
            "Myanmar",
            "Sri Lanka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The Treaty of Sinchula (1865) related to India’s boundary with",
        "answer": "Bhutan",
        "choices": [
            "Bhutan",
            "Nepal",
            "Myanmar",
            "Sri Lanka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The Indus River originates from which of the following places?",
        "answer": "Mansarovar Lake, Tibet",
        "choices": [
            "Mansarovar Lake, Tibet",
            "Kailash Range, Tibet",
            "Gangotri Glacier, Uttrakhand",
            "Karakoram Range, Ladakh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The Chenab River is formed by the confluence of which two rivers?",
        "answer": "Chandra and Bhaga",
        "choices": [
            "Chandra and Bhaga",
            "Jhelum and Ravi",
            "Beas and Sutlej",
            "Indus and Shyok"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which of the following river is known as the Vitasta in ancient texts?",
        "answer": "Jhelum",
        "choices": [
            "Jhelum",
            "Ravi",
            "Chenab",
            "Beas"
        ]
    }
]